Guide to the Daniel A. Collins Papers, 1942-1986 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Daniel A. Collins papers 1942-1986 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Collins, Daniel A.
0.2 linear feet Extent: Approximately 100 Items
Dentist from S.C., first African American on the faculty of the School of Dental Science at the University of San Francisco The Daniel A. Collins Papers span the years 1946-1986 and document aspects of the career and life of Collins, politically active Bay Area resident and the first African American on the faculty of the School of Dental Science at the University of San Francisco. The collection consists of a few items of correspondence; newspaper clippings about personal friends and family members; copies of his transcripts from Berkeley; materials on the history of Meharry Medical College in Nashville, Tennessee, and other documents. The papers also house a folder of records from the Cocoa Merchants' Association of America in which Collins was involved through his import business, Beacol Enterprises, Ltd., for which there are also a few records. Photographs from trips to Indonesia and Africa complete the collection. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
RL.00246
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Daniel A. Collins Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2005.
Chronology List
1916, June 11 Born Darling County, South Carolina
1936 Completed Bachelor of Science degree at Paine College in Augusta, Georgia
1941 Married DeReath Curtis James; completed D.D.S. degree at Meharry Medical College in Nashville, Tennessee
1942-1960 Appointed as assistant professor at the School of Dental Science at the University of San Francisco; first African American on the faculty
1944 Received master's degree in dental science at University of San Francisco
1946 Co-founded the National Urban League's San Francisco Bay Area office, later to be called the Bay Area Urban League.
1954 Co-founder of Lifehouse, a residential and counseling center for people with developmental disabilities, which began under the name of Marin Aid to Retarded Children (MARC); served on their board
1960 Accepted into the Cocoa Merchant Association of America, as director of Beacol Enterprises, Ltd., small Nigerian export company
1965 to 1987 Served on the board of the National Urban League from 1965 to 1987 and vice chairman of the board from 1973 to 1975
1968 Opened a private practice; founded the Oral-Facial Consultative Service, which provided constructive surgery for those with facial deformities; in the same year, became co-publisher of the Sun Reporter newspaper
1989 Awarded the Whitney M. Young Medallion from the National Urban League
1995 Received the Distinguished Alumnus award from the University of California, San Francisco
2007, Sept. 13 Died, age 91, at his home in Mill Valley, California
Collection Overview
The Daniel A. Collins Papers span the years 1946-1986 and document aspects of the career and life of Collins, politically active Bay Area resident and the first African American on the faculty of the School of Dental Science at the University of San Francisco. The collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title or format group, and consists of a few items of correspondence; newspaper clippings about personal friends and family members; copies of his transcripts from Berkeley; materials on the history of Meharry Medical College in Nashville, Tennessee, Collins' 1981 honors program from the Bay Area Urban League, and a few other miscellaneous documents. The collection also houses records from 1956-1961 from the Cocoa Merchants' Association of America in which Collins was involved through his import business, Beacol Enterprises, Ltd., for which there are also a few records. Color snapshots from his 1978 trip to Indonesia and black and white professional photographs taken from his 1960s trips to Africa complete the collection. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Subject Headings
African American dentists -- California; Beacol Enterprises, Ltd; Black-and-white photographs; Cocoa Merchants' Association; Collins, Daniel A.; Color photographs; Dentistry -- United States -- History; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Meharry Medical College (Nashville, Tenn.) -- History; Photographs; University of San Francisco. School of Dental Science -- Faculty
Related Material
Charles DeWitt Watts Papers, 1960-2004 (Pioneering African-American surgeon from Durham, N.C.)
Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collection Library
Robert Edward Dawson Papers, 1939-2006 and n.d (African-American opthalmologist from Durham, N.C. who also graduated from Meharry Medical School; there are many more materials from that school in this collection.)
Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collection Library
Contents of Collection
- Daniel A. Collins Papers, 1942-1986, (1 box)
  - Bay Area Urban League program honoring Collins, 1981 Apr. 7, (3 items) (Box 1)
  - Beacol Enterprises, Ltd. shipping records, 1957-1965, (5 items)
  - Clippings
    - Dr. Daniel Shaw James, 1954 Dec. 4, (1 item)
    - Son's wedding, 1968 Aug. 31, (5 items)
    - The Black Experience of Dan Collins, 1976 June 13, (4 items)
    - Dr. Cleve Eneas, 1982 May 20, (1 item)
    - Lillian and Wilfred Robinson, friends of Collins, 1984 Oct. 21, (1 item)
  - Cocoa Merchants' Association materials, 1956-1961, (32 items)
    Shipping records, revenue and expense reports, bylaws, pamphlets.
  - Correspondence
    - Richard Nixon autograph and letter, 1957 Dec. 11
    - Letter from Brazil, 1975 Dec. 22, (7 items)
  - Grade transcripts, U.C. Berkeley, 1942-1943, (2 items)
  - Materials on Meharry Medical College history and inauguration program, and article on history of African Americans in dentistry, 1959, 1982, 1986, (4 items)
  - Politics - various materials, 1965-1986, (14 items)
    Chiefly printed materials concerning the Peace Corps, House of Representatives, Walter Mondale, United States Senate, signed photograph of Walter Mondale and Geraldine Ferraro.
  - Photographs
    - African trip, 1959-1960 and undated, (4 folders)
      Collins with African associates relating to import businesses at the Christian Enyenaya Arms Hotel Ikeja and other locations. Associates named in captions include Chief Adeye from Nigeria, Anthony Fernandez, and Tom Berkly.
    - Artwork, undated, (7 items)
      Photographs of African artwork include Chief Uwangue, beaded crown, woman standing figure carrying water pot, elephant palm tree with electric lamp, elephant, king and queen bookends, Prince Ohuhn, and fish dish.
    - Indonesia trip, 1978 May, (5 items)
  - Receipt for jewelry purchased by Mrs. D. L. Collins, 1947 Aug. 16